<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<address>
    The PRESIDENT. Mr. Vice President,
    Mr. Speaker, Mr. Chief Justice, Senator
    CooK, Mrs. Eisenhower, and my fellow
    citizens of this great and good country
    we share together:
    When we met here 4 years ago, America
    was bleak in spirit, depressed by the
    prospect of seemingly endless war
    abroad and of destructive conflict at
    home.
    As we meet here today, we stand on
    the threshold of a new era of peace in
    the world. [Applause.]
    The central question before us is: How
    shall we use that peace?
    Let us resolve that this era we are
    about to enter will not be what other
    post-war periods have so often been: a
    time of retreat and isolation that leads
    to stagnation at home and invites new
    danger abroad.
    Let us resolve that this will be what it
    can become: a time of great responsi-
    bilities greatly borne, in which we renew
    the spirit and the promise of America
    as we enter our third century as a nation.
    This past year saw far-reaching re-
    sults from our new policies for peace.
    By continuing to revitalize our tradi-
    tional friendships, and by our missions
    to Peking and to Moscow, we were able
    to establish the base for a new and more
    durable pattern of relationships among
    the nations of the world. Because of
    America's bold initiatives, 1972 will be
    long remembered as the year of the
    greatest progress since the end of World
    War II toward a lasting peace in the
    world. [Applause.]
    The peace we seek in the world is not
    the flimsy peace which is merely an inter-
    lude between wars, but a peace which can
    endure for generations to come.
    It is important that we understand
    both the necessity and the limitations
    of America's role in maintaining that
    peace.
    Unless we in America work to preserve
    the peace, there will be no peace.  
    Unless we in America work to preserve
    freedom, there will be no freedom.
    But let us clearly understand the new
    nature of America's role, as a result of
    the new policies e have adopted over
    these past four years.
    We shall respect our treaty commit-
    ments.
    We shall support vigorously the prin-
    ciple that n.o country has the right to
    impose its will or rule on another by
    force.
    We shall continue, in this era of ne-
    gotiation, to work for the limitation of
    nuclear arms, and to reduce the danger
    of confrontation between the great
    powers.
    We shall do our share in defending
    peace and freedom in the world . .But we
    shall expect others to do their share.
    [Applause.]
    The time has :passed when America
    will make every other nation's conflict
    our own, or make every other nation's
    future our reSPonsibility, or presume to
    tell the people of other nations how to
    manage their own affairs. [Applause.]
    Just as we respect the right of each
    nation to determine its own future, we
    also recognize the responsibility of each
    nation to secure its own futme.
    Just as America's role is indispensab e
    in preserving the wmld's peace, so is each
    nation's role indispensable in preserving
    its own peace.
    Toge er with the rest of the world, let
    us .resolve to move forward from the be-
    ginnings we .have made. Let 'US continue
    to bring down the walls of hostility which
    have divided the world for too long, and
    to build in their place bridges of under-
    standing-'SO that despite profound dif-
    ferences between systems of government.
    the people of the world can be friends.
    [Applause.]
    Let us build a structure of peace in the
    world in which the weak are as safe :as
    the strong-in wllich -each respects the
    right of the ()ther to live by a different
    syste:m--Ul which those who would in-
    fluence others will do so by the strength
    of their ·~ and not by the force of
    their arms.
    Let ll8 accept that high responsibility
    not as a burden.. but gladly-gladly be-
    cause the chance to build such a peace
    is the noblest endeavor in which a na-
    tion ..can engage; gladly, also because
    only if we act greatlY in meeting 'OUr t•e-
    sponsibilities abroad will we remain '8.
    great Nation. and only if we remain a
    great Nation wiU we act greatly in meet-
    ing our challenges home.
    We have the chance today to do more
    than ever oefore in our history to make
    life better 1n America-to ensure better
    education, better health, better housing.
    better transportation~ a cleaner environ-
    ment-to restore respect for law, to make
    our communities more livable-m1d to
    ensure the God-gi~ rlght of every
    Amer·can to full and equal opportunity.
    [Appla.lJse.]
    Because tbe range of our needs is so
    great--becallse the reach of our oppmr-
    tunities is so great-let us be bol~ in our
    determinAtion to meet those needs in .new
    ways.
    Just as building a structure of peace
    abroad has requir«l turning awa;y from
    cld policies tbat failed, so building a
    new era of progress at home requires
    turning away from old policies that have
    failed.
    Abroad, the shift from old policies to
    ne't: has not been a retreat from our re-
    sponsibilities, but a better way to peace.
    And at home, the shift from old poli-
    cies to new will not be a retreat from our
    responsibilities, but a better way to prog-
    ress.
    Abroad and at home, the key to those
    new responsibilities lies in the placing
    and the division of responsibility. We
    have lived too long with the consequences
    of attempting to gather all power and
    responsibility in Washington.
    Abroad and at home, the time has
    come to tum away from the condeseend-
    ing policies of paternalism-of "Wash-
    ington knows best.'.. [Applause.]
    person can be expected to act re-
    sponsibly only if he has responsibility.
    This is buman nature. So let us encour-
    age individuals at home and nations
    abroad to do more for themselves, to de-
    cide more for themselves. Let us locate
    responsibility in more plaoes. Let us
    measure hat we will do for others by
    what they will do for themselves. [Ap-
    plause.]
    That is why today I offer o promise
    of a purely governmental solution for
    every problem. We have lived too long
    with that false promise. In trusting too
    much in government, we have asked -of
    it more than it can deliver. This leads
    only to infiated expectations, to reduced
    individual e.ffort. and to a disappoint-
    ment and frustration that erode con-
    fidence both in what government can do
    and in what people can do.
    Government must learn to take less
    from people so that people can do more
    for themselves. [Applause.]
    Let us remember tbat America was
    built not by government, but by people-
    not by welfare, but by work-not by
    shirking responsibility, but by seeking re-
    sponsibility. [Applause. J
    In our own lives, let each of us ask-
    not just what will government do for me.
    but what can I do for myself'}
    :In the challenges we face together, let
    each of us ask-not just how can govern-
    ment help, but how can I help?
    Your national govemment bas a great
    and vital role to play~ And I pledge to
    you that where this government should
    act, we wm act boldly and we will lead
    boldly. But just :as important is the role
    that each and every one of us must play,
    as an lndividual and as a member of bJs
    own community.
    From this aay forward, let each .of us
    make a solemn commitment in his own
    heart; To bear his responsibility, to do
    his part, to live his ideals-so that to-
    gether.. we can see the dawn of a new age
    of progress for America, and together,
    as we celebrate our 20.0th anniversary as
    a nation, we can do so proud in th~ ful-
    fillment -of our prom1se to ourselves and
    to the world.
    As America's longest and most difficult
    war comes to an end, let us again learn to
    debate our differences with civility and
    decency. IApplause~J And let each of us
    reach out for that one precious quality
    government cannot provide-a new level
    of respect for the rights and feelings of
    one another, a new level of respect for
    the individual human dignity which is
    the cherished birthright of every Ameri-
    can. [Applause.]
    Above all else, the time has come for
    us to renew our faith in ourselves and in
    America.
    In recent years, that faith has been
    challenged.
    Our children have been taught to be
    ashamed of their country, ashamed of
    their parents, ashamed .of America•s rec-
    ord at home and of its role in the world.
    At every turn, we have been beset by
    those who find everything wrong with
    America and little that is right. But I
    am confident that this will not be the
    judgment of history on these remarkable
    times in which we are privileged to live.
    [Applause.]
    Ameriea,s record in this century has
    been unparalleled in the world•s history
    for its responsibility, for its generosity,
    for its creativity and for its progress.
    Let us be proud that our system has
    produced and provided more freedom
    and more .abundance, more widely
    shared, than any other system in the his-
    tory of the world.
    Let us be proud that in each of the
    four wars in which we have been en-
    gaged in this century, including the one
    we are now bringing to an end, we have
    fought not for our selfish advantage, but
    to help others ·resist aggression. [AP-
    plause.]
    Let us be proud that by our bold, new
    initiatives, and by .our -steadfastness for
    peace with honor, we hav.e made a break-
    through toward creating in the world
    what the world has not known before--
    a structure of peace that can last, not
    merely Io!' our time, but for generations
    tooome.
    We are embarking here today on an
    era that presents challenges as great as
    those any nation, or any generation, has
    ever faced.
    We shall answer to God, to history,
    and to our conscience for the way in
    which we use these years.
    As I stand in this place, so hallowed
    by history, I think of others who have
    stood here before me. I think of the
    dreams they had for America, and I
    think of how each recognized that he
    needed help far beyond himself in order
    to make those dreams come true.
    Today. I ask your prayen; that in the
    years ahead I may have God's help in
    making decisions that .are right tor
    America, and I pray for your help so
    that together we may be worthy of our
    challenge.
    Let us pledge together to make these
    next four years the best four years in
    America's history so that on its 200th
    birthday Amelica will be as yotmg and as
    vital as when it began, and as bright a
    beacon of hope for all the world.
    Let us go forward from here confident
    in hope. strang in our faith in one an-
    other, sustained by our faith in God 'Who
    created us, and striving always to serve
    His purpose.
</address>
