<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="file:/Users/taishanahan/Desktop/Pres-Inaug-Project/Address_Schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<address president="George H.W. Bush" term="1" party="R">
    <introduction>Mr. FORD. Ladies and gentlemen, the President of the United States.</introduction>

    <speech>
        <paragraph>Mr. Chief Justice, Mr. President, Vice President QuAYLE, Senator MITCHELL,
            Speaker WRIGHT, Senator DoLE, Congressman MICHEL, and fellow citizens, neighbors, and
            friends.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>There is a man here who has earned a lasting place in our hearts-and in our
            history. President Reagan, on behalf of our Nation, I thank you for the wonderful things
            that you have done for America.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>I have just repeated, word for word, the oath taken by George Washington 200
            years ago; and the Bible on which I placed my hand is the Bible on which he placed
            his.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>It is right that the memory of Washington be with us today, not only because this
            is our Bicentennial Inauguration, but because Washington remains the Father of our
            country. And he would, I think, be gladdened by this day, for today is the concrete
            expres- form of government is better. We sion of a stunning fact: our continuity don't
            have to wrest justice from the these 200 years since our Government began. </paragraph>

        <paragraph>We meet on democracy's front porch, a good place to talk as neighbors and as
            friends. For this is a day when our Nation is made whole, when our differences for a
            moment are suspended.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>And my first act as president is a prayer. I ask you to bow your
            heads:</paragraph>

        <paragraph>Heavenly Father, we bow our heads and thank You for Your love. Accept our thanks
            for the peace that yields this day and the shared faith that makes its continuance
            likely. Male us strong to do Your work, willing to heed and hear Your will, and write on
            our hearts these words, "Use power to help people." For we are given power not to
            advance our own purposes, nor to make a great show in your name. There is but one jusr
            use of power, and it is to serve people. Help us to remember it, Lord. Amen.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>I come before you and assume the Presidenct at a moment rich with promise. We
            live in a peaceful, prosperous time, but we can make it better. For a new breeze is
            blowing, and a world refreshed by freedom seems reborn; for in a man's heart, if not in
            fact, the day of the dictator is over.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>The totalitarian era is passing, its old ideas blown away like leaves from an
            ancient, lifeless tree.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>A new breeze is blowing-and a nation refreshed by freedom stands ready to push
            on: There is new ground to be broken, and new action to be taken.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>There are times when the future seems thick as a fog; you sit and wait, hoping
            the mists will lift and reveal the right path.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>But this is a time when the future seems a door you can walk right through-into a
            room called tomorrow.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>Great nations of the world are moving toward democracy-through the door to
            freedom.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>Men and women of the world move towards free markets-through the door to
            prosperity.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>The people of the world agitate for free expression and free thought-through the
            door to the moral and intellectual satisfactions that only liberty allows.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>We know what works: Freedom works. We know what's right: Freedom is right. We
            know how to secure a more just and prosperous life for man on Earth: through free
            markets, free speech, free elections, and the exercise of free will unhampered by the
            state.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>For the first time in this century-for the firdt time in perhaps all history-man
            does not have to invent a system by which to live. We don't have to talk late into the
            night about which form of government is better. We don't have to wrestle justice from
            the kings. We only have to summon it from within ourselves.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>We must act on what we know. I take as my guide the hope of a saint: In crucial
            things, unity; in important things, diversity; in all things, generosity.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>America today is a proud, free Nation, decent and civil-a place we cannot help
            but love. We know in our hearts, not loudly and proudly, but as a simple fact, that this
            country has meaning beyond what we see, and that our strength is a force for
            good.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>But have we changed as a nation even in our time? Are we enthralled with material
            things, less appreciative of the nobility of work and sacrifice?</paragraph>

        <paragraph>My friends, we are not the sum of our possessions. They are not the measure of
            our lives. In our hearts we know what matters. We cannot hope to leave our children a
            bigger car, a bigger bank account. We must hope to give them a sense of what it means to
            be a loyal friend, a loving parent, a citizen who leaves his home, his neighborhood, and
            town better than he found it.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>What do we want the men and women who with with us to say when we are no longer
            there? That we were more driven to succeed than anyone around us? Or that we stopped to
            ask if a sick child had gotten better, and stayed a moment there to trade a word of
            friendship?</paragraph>

        <paragraph>No president, no government, can teach us to remember what is best in what we
            are. But if the man you have chosen to lead this government can help make a difference;
            if he can celebrate the quieter, deeper successes that are made not of gold and silk,
            but of better hearts and finer souls; if he can do these things, then he
            must.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>America is never wholly herself unless she is engaged in high morale principle.
            We as a people have such a purpose today. It is to make kinder the face of the Nation
            and gentler the face of the world.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>My friends, we have work to do.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>There are the homeless, lost and roaming; there are the children who have
            nothing, no love, no normalcy; there are those who cannot free themselves of enslavement
            to whatever addiction-drugs, welfare, the demoralization that rules the slums. There is
            crime to be conquered, the rough crime of the streets. There are young women to be
            helped who are about tobecome mothers of children they can't care for and might not
            love. They need our care, our guidance, and our education; though we bless them for
            choosing life.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>The old solution, the old way, was to think that public money alone could end
            these problems. But we have learned that is not so. And in any case, our funds are low.
            We have a deficit to bring down. We have more will than wallet; but will is what we
            need. We will make the hard choices, looking at what we have and perhaps allocating it
            differently, making our decisions based on honest need and prudent safety. And then we
            will do the wisest thing of all: We will turn to the only resource we have that in times
            of need always grows--the goodness and the courage of the American people.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>I am speaking of a new engagement in the lives of others, a new activism,
            hands-on and involved, that gets the job done. We must bring in the generations,
            harnessing the unused talent of the elderly and the unfocused energy of the young. For
            not only leadership is passed from generation to generation, but so is stewardship. And
            the generation born after the Second World War has come of age.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>I have spoken of a thousand points of light, of all the community organizations
            that are spread like stars throughout the Nation, doing good. We will work hand in hand,
            encouraging, sometimes leading, sometimes being led, rewarding. We will work on this in
            the White House, in the Cabinet agencies. I will go to the people and the programs that
            are the brighter points of light, and I will ask every member of my government to become
            involved. The old ideas are new again because they are not old, they are timeless: duty,
            sacrifice, commitment, and a patriotism that finds its expression in taking part and
            pitching in.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>We need a new engagement, too, between the Executive and the Congress. The
            challenges before us will be thrashed out with the House and the Senate. We must bring
            the Federal budget into balance. And we must ensure that America stands before the world
            united, strong, at peace, and fiscally sound. But, of course, things may be difficult.
            We need compromise; we have had dissension. We need harmony; we have had a chorus of
            discordant voices.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>For Congress, too, has changed in our time. There has grown a certain
            divisiveness. We have seen the hard looks and heard the statements in which not each
            other's ideas are challenged, but each other's motives. And our great parties have too
            often been far apart and untrusting of each other. It has been this way since Vietnam.
            That war cleaves us still. But, friends, that war began in earnest a quarter of a
            century ago; and surely the statute of limitations has been reached. This is a fact: The
            final lesson of Vietnam is that no great nation can long afford to be sundered by a
            memory. A new breeze is blowing, and the old bipartisanship must be made new
            again.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>To my friends--and yes, I do mean friends--in the loyal opposition--and yes, I
            mean loyal: I put out my hand. I am putting out my hand to you, Mr. Speaker. I am
            putting out my hand to you Mr. Majority Leader. For this is the thing: This is the age
            of the offered hand. We can't turn back clocks, and I don't want to. But when our
            fathers were young, Mr. Speaker, our differences ended at the water's edge. And we don't
            wish to turn back time, but when our mothers were young, Mr. Majority Leader, the
            Congress and the Executive were capable of working together to produce a budget on which
            this nation could live. Let us negotiate soon and hard. But in the end, let us produce.
            The American people await action. They didn't send us here to bicker. They ask us to
            rise above the merely partisan. "In crucial things, unity"--and this, my friends, is
            crucial.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>To the world, too, we offer new engagement and a renewed vow: We will stay strong
            to protect the peace. The "offered hand" is a reluctant fist; but once made, strong, and
            can be used with great effect. There are today Americans who are held against their will
            in foreign lands, and Americans who are unaccounted for. Assistance can be shown here,
            and will be long remembered. Good will begets good will. Good faith can be a spiral that
            endlessly moves on.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>Great nations like great men must keep their word. When America says something,
            America means it, whether a treaty or an agreement or a vow made on marble steps. We
            will always try to speak clearly, for candor is a compliment, but subtlety, too, is good
            and has its place. While keeping our alliances and friendships around the world strong,
            ever strong, we will continue the new closeness with the Soviet Union, consistent both
            with our security and with progress. One might say that our new relationship in part
            reflects the triumph of hope and strength over experience. But hope is good, and so are
            strength and vigilance.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>Here today are tens of thousands of our citizens who feel the understandable
            satisfaction of those who have taken part in democracy and seen their hopes fulfilled.
            But my thoughts have been turning the past few days to those who would be watching at
            home, to an older fellow who will throw a salute by himself when the flag goes by, and
            the women who will tell her sons the words of the battle hymns. I don't mean this to be
            sentimental. I mean that on days like this, we remember that we are all part of a
            continuum, inescapably connected by the ties that bind.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>Our children are watching in schools throughout our great land. And to them I
            say, thank you for watching democracy's big day. For democracy belongs to us all, and
            freedom is like a beautiful kite that can go higher and higher with the breeze. And to
            all I say: No matter what your circumstances or where you are, you are part of this day,
            you are part of the life of our great nation.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>A President is neither prince nor pope, and I don't seek a window on men's souls.
            In fact, I yearn for a greater tolerance, an easy-goingness about each other's attitudes
            and way of life.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>There are few clear areas in which we as a society must rise up united and
            express our intolerance. The most obvious now is drugs. And when that first cocaine was
            smuggled in on a ship, it may as well have been a deadly bacteria, so much has it hurt
            the body, the soul of our country. And there is much to be done and to be said, but take
            my word for it: This scourge will stop.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>And so, there is much to do; and tomorrow the work begins. I do not mistrust the
            future; I do not fear what is ahead. For our problems are large, but our heart is
            larger. Our challenges are great, but our will is greater. And if our flaws are endless,
            God's love is truly boundless.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>Some see leadership as high drama, and the sound of trumpets calling, and
            sometimes it is that. But I see history as a book with many pages, and each day we fill
            a page with acts of hopefulness and meaning. The new breeze blows, a page turns, the
            story unfolds. And so today a chapter begins, a small and stately story of unity,
            diversity, and generosity--shared, and written, together.</paragraph>

        <paragraph>Thank you. God bless you and God bless the United States of America.</paragraph>
    </speech>
</address>
